What if I told you there was something that you can do right now
만약 뇌에 즉각적으로 긍정적인 영향을 미치는
that would have an immediate, positive benefit for your brain
행동을 지금 당장 할 수 있다면 어떻게 하시겠습니까?
including your mood and your focus?
기분과 집중력까지 좋아진다면요?
And what if I told you that same thing could actually last a long time
효과가 장시간 지속되어
and protect your brain from different conditions
뇌 질환으로부터 여러분이 보호받을 수 있다면요?
like depression, Alzheimer's disease or dementia.
우울증, 알츠하이머, 치매와 같은 병이요.
Would you do it?
시도해보시겠습니까?
Yes!
네!
I am talking about the powerful effects of physical activity.
강력한 신체 활동의 효과에 대해 이야기하고자 합니다.
Simply moving your body,
몸을 움직이는 것만으로도
has immediate, long-lasting and protective benefits for your brain.
뇌에 즉각적이고 오래 지속되는 보호 효과를 경험할 수 있습니다.
And that can last for the rest of your life.
이 효과가 평생 유지될 수도 있고요.
So what I want to do today is tell you a story
제가 여러분에게 들려 드릴 이야기는
about how I used my deep understanding of neuroscience,
신경과학에 대한 깊은 이해에 관한 겁니다.
as a professor of neuroscience,
신경과학 교수로서
to essentially do an experiment on myself
스스로 실천했던 실험의 결과이지요.
in which I discovered the science underlying
이 실험을 통해 뇌를 즉시 변화시키는
why exercise is the most transformative thing
가장 혁신적인 활동인 운동의
that you can do for your brain today.
과학적인 근거를 발견하였습니다.
Now, as a neuroscientist, I know that our brains,
신경과학자로서
that is the thing in our head right now,
지금 머릿속에 있는 바로 그 뇌가
that is the most complex structure known to humankind.
인류가 아는 가장 복잡한 구조의 기관이라는 사실을 압니다.
But it's one thing to talk about the brain,
뇌에 대해 말하는 것과
and it's another to see it.
뇌를 직접 보는 것은 다릅니다.
So here is a real preserved human brain.
실제 인간의 뇌를 보존한 모습입니다.
And it's going to illustrate two key areas that we are going to talk about today.
오늘 이야기할 두 가지 핵심이 여기에 있습니다.
The first is the prefrontal cortex, right behind your forehead,
첫째는, 이마 바로 뒤에 자리한 전전두엽 피질입니다.
critical for things like decision-making, focus, attention and your personality.
의사결정, 집중, 주의, 성격을 결정하는 중요한 역할을 합니다.
The second key area is located in the temporal lobe, shown right here.
둘째는, 측두엽에 있습니다.
You have two temporal lobes in your brain, the right and the left,
뇌에는 좌우 양쪽에 측두엽이 있습니다.
and deep in the temporal lobe is a key structure
측두엽 깊숙한 곳에
critical for your ability
사실과 사건을 장기기억으로 형성하고 저장하는데
to form and retain new long-term memories for facts and events.
중요한 핵심 영역이 있습니다.
And that structure is called the hippocampus.
그 부위가 바로 해마입니다.
So I've always been fascinated with the hippocampus.
저는 늘 해마에 열광했습니다.
How could it be that an event that lasts just a moment,
찰나의 순간에 일어난 사건
say, your first kiss,
예를 들어 첫 키스와
or the moment your first child was born,
첫 아이가 태어난 순간이
can form a memory that has changed your brain,
뇌에 어떤 변화를 일으켰기에
that lasts an entire lifetime?
평생 지워지지 않는 기억으로 저장될 수 있었을까요?
That's what I want to understand.
여기에 대한 답을 찾고 싶었습니다.
I wanted to start and record the activity of individual brain cells
저는 해마 속 뇌세포가 새로운 기억을 형성하는 동안
in the hippocampus
해마영역에 일어나는 뇌세포의 활동을 기록하고자 했습니다.
as subjects were forming new memories.
신경세포 간의 정보전달을 가능하게 한
And essentially try and decode how those brief bursts of electrical activity,
순간의 전기적 신호를 해석하는데 집중했습니다.
which is how neurons communicate with each other,
순간의 전기신호의 어떤 작용이
how those brief bursts either allowed us to form a new memory, or did not.
새로운 기억의 생성여부를 결정짓는지를 연구했습니다.
But a few years ago, I did something very unusual in science.
그러나 몇 해 전, 저는 과학계에서 이례적인 선택을 했습니다.
As a full professor of neural science,
신경 과학 전임교수였던 저는
I decided to completely switch my research program.
연구 계획을 전면 변경하기로 결정했습니다.
Because I encountered something that was so amazing,
놀라운 발견을 했기 때문이었어요.
with the potential to change so many lives
수많은 이들의 삶을 변화시킬 잠재력이 있는 주제였기에,
that I had to study it.
반드시 연구하고 싶었습니다.
I discovered and I experienced the brain-changing effects of exercise.
저는 경험을 통해 뇌를 변화시키는 운동의 효과를 발견하였습니다.
And I did it in a completely inadvertent way.
완벽히 우연한 계기로요.
I was actually at the height of all the memory work that I was doing --
뇌 기억 기능에 관한 연구가 한창이던 시기였죠.
data was pouring in,
자료는 쏟아졌고
I was becoming known in my field for all of this memory work.
기억 분야에서 제 이름을 알리기 시작할 때였습니다.
And it should have been going great. It was, scientifically.
과학적인 사고로는, 좋은 시기가 분명했습니다.
But when I stuck my head out of my lab door,
그러나 연구실 문을 열고 나왔을 때
I noticed something.
이런 생각이 들었습니다.
I had no social life.
제겐 일 외의 삶이 없더군요.
I spent too much time listening to those brain cells
온종일 뇌세포에 모든 주의를 기울인 채
in a dark room, by myself.
어두운 방 안에 앉아있었죠. 혼자요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
I didn't move my body at all.
몸을 전혀 움직이지 않았어요.
I had gained 25 pounds.
살이 25파운드나 쪘었고요.
And actually, it took me many years to realize it,
제 상태를 깨닫기까지 수 년이 걸렸습니다.
I was actually miserable.
전 비참한 상태였어요.
And I shouldn't be miserable.
하지만 비참해지고 싶지 않았어요.
And I went on a river-rafting trip -- by myself, because I had no social life.
혼자 강 래프팅 여행을 갔습니다. 친구가 없으니까요.
And I came back --
래프팅 후 돌아와서
(Laughter)
(웃음)
thinking, "Oh, my God, I was the weakest person on that trip."
생각했습니다. "세상에, 내가 체력이 가장 약했어."
And I came back with a mission.
저 자신에게 한 가지 임무를 부여했습니다.
I said, "I'm never going to feel like the weakest person
"다음에 다시 이런 래프팅을 한다면
on a river-rafting trip again."
절대 최약체가 되지 말아야지" 라고요.
And that's what made me go to the gym.
그래서 헬스장에 다니기 시작했습니다.
And I focused my type-A personality
제 소심한 성격에 집중했습니다.
on going to all the exercise classes at the gym.
헬스장 모든 운동프로그램을 들었죠.
I tried everything.
다 해봤습니다.
I went to kickbox, dance, yoga, step class,
킥복싱, 댄스, 요가, 스텝 에어로빅스.
and at first it was really hard.
처음에는 정말 힘들었습니다.
But what I noticed is that after every sweat-inducing workout that I tried,
하지만 땀 흘려 운동을 하고 나면
I had this great mood boost and this great energy boost.
항상 기분이 좋아지고 에너지가 상승했습니다.
And that's what kept me going back to the gym.
그래서 계속 헬스장에 갔죠.
Well, I started feeling stronger.
스스로 강해졌다고 느끼기 시작했어요.
I started feeling better, I even lost that 25 pounds.
기분도 더 좋았고, 25파운드(약 10kg)도 감량했습니다.
And now, fast-forward a year and a half into this regular exercise program
1년 반 전부터, 규칙적으로 운동을 시작하면서
and I noticed something that really made me sit up and take notice.
중요한 깨달음을 얻은 순간이 있었습니다.
I was sitting at my desk, writing a research grant,
책상에 앉아 연구 보조금 기획안을 작성 중이었죠.
and a thought went through my mind
이제껏 한 번도 겪어보지 못했던
that had never gone through my mind before.
생각이 머리를 스쳤습니다.
And that thought was,
그것은 바로
"Gee, grant-writing is going well today."
"어머나, 연구지원서가 정말 잘 써지는데."
And all the scientists --
모든 과학자가
(Laughter)
(웃음)
yeah, all the scientists always laugh when I say that,
이 말을 들으면 모든 과학자가 웃습니다.
because grant-writing never goes well.
연구지원서는 결코 잘 써지는 법이 없어요.
It is so hard; you're always pulling your hair out,
너무 어려워서 늘 머리를 쥐어짜며
trying to come up with that million-dollar-winning idea.
거액의 연구 보조금을 확보할 만한 아이디어를 구상합니다.
But I realized that the grant-writing was going well,
그런데 정말 잘 써졌어요.
because I was able to focus and maintain my attention
예전보다 더 오래 집중하고
for longer than I had before.
집중력을 유지할 수도 있었어요.
And my long-term memory -- what I was studying in my own lab --
실험실에서 연구했던 주제인 저의 장기기억도
seemed to be better in me.
더 향상된 듯 보였습니다.
And that's when I put it together.
그제야 이해가 되더군요.
Maybe all that exercise that I had included and added to my life
혹시 내 인생에 새로이 들어온 운동이라는 영역이
was changing my brain.
뇌를 변화시킨 것은 아닐까?
Maybe I did an experiment on myself without even knowing it.
나도 모르는 사이에 스스로 실험을 한 것이었죠.
So as a curious neuroscientist,
신경과학자의 호기심을 발동하여
I went to the literature to see what I could find about what we knew
뇌에 미치는 운동의 효과에 관한
about the effects of exercise on the brain.
문헌을 찾아보았습니다.
And what I found was an exciting and a growing literature
저 자신에게 일어났던 변화를 뒷받침해주는
that was essentially showing everything that I noticed in myself.
흥미로운 문헌들이 많았습니다.
Better mood, better energy, better memory, better attention.
운동을 하면 기분, 기력, 기억력, 주의력이 향상되었습니다.
And the more I learned,
더 깊이 연구하면 할수록
the more I realized how powerful exercise was.
운동의 강력한 능력을 깨달았습니다.
Which eventually led me to the big decision
이것이 동기가 되어, 연구 주제를 완전히 전환하는
to completely shift my research focus.
중대한 결정을 하게되었습니다.
And so now, after several years of really focusing on this question,
이 질문에 몰두한 지 몇 년이 흐른 현재
I've come to the following conclusion:
다음과 같은 결론에 이르렀습니다.
that exercise is the most transformative thing
운동은 우리가 당장 실천할 수 있는
that you can do for your brain today
뇌를 변화시키는 혁신적인 활동입니다.
for the following three reasons.
여기에 세 가지 근거가 있습니다.
Number one: it has immediate effects on your brain.
첫째, 운동은 뇌에 즉각적인 영향을 미칩니다.
A single workout that you do
단 한 번의 운동이
will immediately increase levels of neurotransmitters
즉시 신경전달물질 분비를 촉진합니다.
like dopamine, serotonin and noradrenaline.
도파민, 세로토닌, 노르아드레날린 등이요.
That is going to increase your mood right after that workout,
운동이 끝나면, 신경전달물질이 기분을 상승시킵니다.
exactly what I was feeling.
제가 느꼈던 그대로요.
My lab showed that a single workout
실험을 통해, 한 번의 운동만으로
can improve your ability to shift and focus attention,
민첩성과 집중력이 향상됨을 확인하였습니다.
and that focus improvement will last for at least two hours.
집중력 향상 효과는 최소 2시간 동안 지속되었죠.
And finally, studies have shown
마지막으로, 운동으로 반응 속도도
that a single workout will improve your reaction times
향상된다는 연구결과가 나왔습니다.
which basically means
다시 말해서
that you are going to be faster at catching that cup of Starbucks
바에서 떨어지는 중인, 스타벅스 커피잔을
that falls off the counter,
더 잽싸게 잡을 수 있다는 뜻입니다.
which is very, very important.
매우 중요한 점이죠.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
But these immediate effects are transient, they help you right after.
그러나 운동 직후에 나타나는 즉각 효과는 일시적입니다.
What you have to do is do what I did,
제가 했던 방식을 따라 해보십시오.
that is change your exercise regime, increase your cardiorespiratory function,
운동법을 바꾸어 보세요.
to get the long-lasting effects.
장기간 지속되는 심폐기능 강화 효과를 경험해보십시오.
And these effects are long-lasting
운동이 뇌의 해부학적 구조와
because exercise actually changes the brain's anatomy,
생리 및 기능을 변화시켜
physiology and function.
효과가 장기간 지속될 수 있습니다.
Let's start with my favorite brain area, the hippocampus.
제가 좋아하는 뇌 영역인 해마에서 시작해봅시다.
The hippocampus --
해마
or exercise actually produces brand new brain cells,
운동으로 새로운 뇌세포가 생성됩니다.
new brain cells in the hippocampus, that actually increase its volume,
해마의 새로운 뇌세포의 양이 증가하면
as well as improve your long-term memory, OK?
장기 기억력이 향상합니다.
And that including in you and me.
저와 여러분, 모두에게 해당합니다.
Number two: the most common finding in neuroscience studies,
둘째, 장기간 운동을 했을 때 나타난
looking at effects of long-term exercise,
신경과학 연구의 가장 보편적인 결과로는
is improved attention function dependent on your prefrontal cortex.
전전두엽 피질이 역할이 중요한 주의력 향상이 있습니다.
You not only get better focus and attention,
이때, 주의집중력이 개선될 뿐만 아니라
but the volume of the hippocampus increases as well.
해마의 부피도 커집니다.
And finally, you not only get immediate effects of mood with exercise
그 결과, 운동 직후 나타난 기분 전환 효과가
but those last for a long time.
오랫동안 지속될 수 있습니다.
So you get long-lasting increases in those good mood neurotransmitters.
활기찬 감정을 주는 신경전달물질의 분비가 지속해서 증가하게 되죠.
But really, the most transformative thing that exercise will do
그러나 운동의 가장 혁신적인 효과는
is its protective effects on your brain.
뇌의 보호기능 향상입니다.
Here you can think about the brain like a muscle.
뇌를 일종의 근육이라고 생각해봅시다.
The more you're working out,
운동을 더 많이 할 수록
the bigger and stronger your hippocampus and prefrontal cortex gets.
해마와 전전두엽 피질은 더 커지고 강해집니다.
Why is that important?
이 점이 왜 중요할까요?
Because the prefrontal cortex and the hippocampus
전전두엽 피질과 해마는
are the two areas that are most susceptible to neurodegenerative diseases
신경변성 질환과 노화로 인한 인지력 감퇴에
and normal cognitive decline in aging.
가장 예민한 뇌 부위이기 때문입니다.
So with increased exercise over your lifetime,
물론, 평생 운동량을 늘린다고 하여
you're not going to cure dementia or Alzheimer's disease,
치매나 알츠하이머를 완치할 수는 없습니다.
but what you're going to do is you're going to create
그러나 운동을 통해 우리는 가장 강력하고
the strongest, biggest hippocampus and prefrontal cortex
가장 큰 해마와 전전두엽 피질을 생성할 수 있습니다.
so it takes longer for these diseases to actually have an effect.
퇴행성 뇌 질환이 실제로 발병하기까지 오랜 시간이 걸리죠.
You can think of exercise, therefore,
그러므로 우리는 운동을
as a supercharged 401K for your brain, OK?
뇌건강을 위한 빵빵한 퇴직연금으로 생각할 수 있겠네요.
And it's even better, because it's free.
운동은 공짜니까 심지어 더 좋죠.
So this is the point in the talk where everybody says,
이쯤이면 사람들은 이런 질문을 합니다.
"That sounds so interesting, Wendy,
"웬디, 정말 흥미로운 이야기네요.
but I really will only want to know one thing.
사실 정말 궁금한 건 딱 한 가지예요.
And that is, just tell me the minimum amount of exercise
당신이 말한 변화를 경험하는 데 필요한
I need to get all these changes."
최소한의 운동량을 알려주세요."
(Laughter)
(웃음)
And so I'm going to tell you the answer to that question.
그 질문에 대한 답을 드리겠습니다.
First, good news: you don't have to become a triathlete to get these effects.
철인 3종 경기선수가 될 필요는 없습니다.
The rule of thumb is you want to get three to four times a week exercise
경험상, 일주일에 최소 30분간
minimum 30 minutes an exercise session,
3~4회 운동이면 충분합니다.
and you want to get aerobic exercise in.
여기에 유산소 운동을 포함하세요.
That is, get your heart rate up.
심장 박동을 높이는 운동을 하십시오.
And the good news is, you don't have to go to the gym
좋은 소식은, 굳이 헬스장에 가서
to get a very expensive gym membership.
고가의 회원권을 끊지 않아도 된다는 것이죠.
Add an extra walk around the block in your power walk.
파워 워킹으로 주변 단지를 산책하세요.
You see stairs -- take stairs.
계단이 보이면, 계단을 오르세요.
And power-vacuuming can be as good as the aerobics class
진공청소기를 힘차게 돌리는 것도
that you were going to take at the gym.
헬스장에서 에어로빅 수업을 듣는 것만큼 좋습니다.
So I've gone from memory pioneer
저는 기억 개척자로 출발해
to exercise explorer.
운동 탐험가가 되었습니다.
From going into the innermost workings of the brain,
뇌의 가장 중심부를 파고들어
to trying to understand how exercise can improve our brain function,
운동이 어떻게 뇌 기능을 향상시키지는 알고자 했습니다.
and my goal in my lab right now
현재 저의 연구 목적은
is to go beyond that rule of thumb that I just gave you --
여러분께 방금 제시했던 경험법칙을 넘어서는데 있죠.
three to four times a week, 30 minutes.
일주일에 30분간 3~4회가 아닌
I want to understand the optimum exercise prescription
맞춤형 최적의 운동처방을 제시하는데 있습니다.
for you, at your age, at your fitness level,
개인의 연령과 체력 수준
for your genetic background,
유전적 배경을 고려한 처방으로
to maximize the effects of exercise today
운동 효과를 극대화하고
and also to improve your brain and protect your brain the best
뇌 기능을 향상하여, 남은 생애 동안
for the rest of your life.
뇌를 가장 잘 보호할 수 있는 방법을 찾고자 합니다.
But it's one thing to talk about exercise, and it's another to do it.
운동에 관해 이야기하는 것과 실천은 다른 얘기죠.
So I'm going to invoke my power as a certified exercise instructor,
자격증을 취득한 운동강사인 제가 힘을 발휘해볼게요.
to ask you all to stand up.
모두 자리에서 일어나 주세요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
We're going to do just one minute of exercise.
다 함께 1분 동안 운동합시다.
It's call-and-response, just do what I do, say what I say,
제가 외치면 여러분이 따라 하세요.
and make sure you don't punch your neighbor, OK?
옆 사람은 치지마세요.
Music!
음악 주세요!
(Upbeat music)
(신나는 음악)
Five, six, seven, eight, it's right, left, right, left.
5, 6, 7, 8, 오른쪽, 왼쪽, 오른쪽, 왼쪽
And I say, I am strong now.
나는 지금 강하다.
Let's hear you.
외치세요.
Audience: I am strong now.
관객: 나는 지금 강하다.
Wendy Suzuki: Ladies, I am Wonder Woman-strong.
웬디 스즈키: 여자분들, 나는 원더우먼처럼 강하다.
Let's hear you!
외칩니다.
Audience: I am Wonder Woman-strong.
관객: 나는 원더우먼처럼 강하다.
WS: New move -- uppercut, right and left.
웬디 스즈키: 동작을 바꿔서 올려치기, 오른쪽, 왼쪽.
I am inspired now. You say it!
나는 영감 받았다. 다 함께!
Audience: I am inspired now.
관객: 나는 영감받았다.
WS: Last move -- pull it down, right and left, right and left.
웬디: 마지막 동작. 손 내리세요. 오른손 왼손, 오른손 왼손.
I say, I am on fire now! You say it.
완전히 탄력받았어! 다함께!
Audience: I am on fire now.
관객: 완전히 탄력받았어!
WS: And done! OK, good job!
웬디: 훌륭해요. 굉장해요!
(Applause)
(박수)
Thank you.
감사합니다.
I want to leave you with one last thought.
끝으로 한 가지만 말씀드리겠습니다.
And that is, bringing exercise in your life
여러분의 삶에 운동을 포함하세요.
will not only give you a happier, more protective life today,
운동은 더 행복하고 보호받는 오늘의 삶을 선사할 뿐만 아니라
but it will protect your brain from incurable diseases.
난치병으로부터 여러분의 뇌를 보호해줄 것입니다.
And in this way it will change the trajectory of your life
운동은 우리의 삶을 더 나은 궤도에
for the better.
올려놓을 것입니다.
Thank you very much.
감사합니다.
(Applause)
(박수)